Right. So, welcome back everyone. So,
after we've seen, you know, how to
define and simulate ur masses and
external sources, now we're basically
are going to combine uh you
know uh elements of these types, these
three types in different combinations to
create circuits.
And uh the the outline for this session
is essentially we're going to go through
two examples from the literature. Uh the
first one is from our own lab uh
developed by Anand here uh leading it
and that is a biometric model of
corticistal micro assemblies. Uh you've
seen the full model in lily talk on the
first day doing category learning. Today
you will build a subset of that model
and you will see how the hierarchical
structure in neuroblocks actually works.
And the second example is a is a ping
model and the ping stands for pyramal
inter neuron uh gamma rhythms right so
that's that's a network of you know
pyramal neurons and inter neurons
interacting with each other and
generating gamma gamma rhythms.
So uh first let's move on to the to the
cortical model. Um so yeah as I was
saying this is you've seen the full
model and the full model was based on
you know mechanistic principles about
you know how the brain behavior should
actually incorporate any inter relations
across multiple scales and the multiple
scales here are you know starting from
uh neural receptors right uh neural
activity of individual neurons and then
up to behavior right because this model
is able to both take in input from the
outside work world in the form of images
and also output actions you know left
right decisions and it works across the
sca these three
scales. Uh and yeah here you can find
also the reference uh to this model and
this model was uh well the first big
model to be designed entirely within
your blocks.
Um you probably have seen this graph
before and this is the graph of the
complete model uh incorporating both you
know cortic cortical components uh two
of them and also subcortical components
multiple different ones each one serving
a different function uh a subset of
these you you will see in the exercises
today. So this model has been uh you
know there's a lot of like biohysical
knowledge go given into this model. So
it has been constrained by biology both
in its parameters and also in its
structure in you know how the blocks
connect with each other. uh you will see
that in the connection rules for
cortical blocks and uh after has been
built like this you know following any
in constraints that we have from the
literature from biology it can actually
it exhibits this bottomup emergence uh
where actually it can it matches
observed behavior and brain dynamics uh
starting from you know cell level
physiology in the in the macak brain so
it's important to note that this model
has never been fitted to date to macak
data but it can still match data both on
the electrophysiological level and also
on the behavioral level. So and the
story of the model is essentially moving
from you know synapses to local
assemblies of neurons brain regions and
to bigger brain circuits and in fact you
will move across uh these scales in the
in the first exercise
today. Um so as I was saying uh you will
build a subset of this model. This
subset will include two cortical
components u one for the visual cortex
and one for the arterial cortex and you
will also add an ascending system
component that's brain stem uh you know
modulating the the spiking rhythm for
the cortex and also later on you will
you will add the the image stimul uh to
this
um so you will build the model from from
the bottom up. So you will start from
you know single neurons and at the
smallest level we have this superficial
cortical uh layer for lateral
inhibition. You can see a schematic of
this down here where we have essentially
uh four excitatory neurons and one
feedback uh inter neuron. And as you can
see all exciting neurons connect to the
to the inter neuron and the inter neuron
connects back to all of them. And this
establishes this uh this type of winner
take all competition. Whereas you can
see in this uh stack block here. This by
the way is a blood that you can generate
u entirely within your blocks. You will
see how um you can see that the inter
neuron is you know remains tonically
active right and some some of the
excited excitatory neurons you know
spiked. You know the initial conditions
are randomized here but only one won
right because it spiked as you can see
it spiked more frequently to begin with
and so this one wins and uh this this
you know spike timings that were you
know more frequent to begin with enable
this one to keep spiking and because it
connects to the inter neuron and the
inter neuron connects to all other
excitatory neurons then the the inter
neuron shuts down the rest of the excit
excitatory neurons right so This is the
winner takes all uh this the last
accepttor has clearly won in this case
and you can do also loads of you know uh
functions by uh stitching multiple of
these assemblies together and you will
see how that works in learning as well.
Now
um yeah as I was saying it's only the
pyramal neuron essentially with the
strongest input at a given time that's
allowed to spike and everything else is
being inhibited by this single inhibitor
neuron. So moving one layer up in the
hierarchy uh we will connect multiple of
these you know winner takes all blocks
together and essentially that
constitutes a cortical blocks right so
in this schematic you can see it's
essentially uh six of these winner take
all blocks connected together again you
will see the connection rule between
them
um and yeah again here is a schematic of
a stack plot where you can see that you
know it's usually um one excit
uh neuron winning over over the rest uh
with across its uh WTA block. Right? So
the blue colors are always excitatory
neurons and the red ones are the
inhibitor
ones. So uh keep going up on the
hierarchy. We will uh connect two
cortical blocks together, right? Each
one holding these multiple uh where it
takes all secrets. one cortical blocks
will represent visual cortex and the
other one is going to present the
anterior cortex um connected one way so
visual connects to anterior of course
there's going to be an iman stimulus
connecting to the visual cortex and
finally there is the the brain stem this
is the ascending system input uh that uh
actually connects on to both cortices
and modulates their
activity and here I'm just showing you
some examples of u essentially plotting
recipes you visualization options that
we include in your blocks and that you
will use uh in the circuits day now and
these are particularly useful for
assemblies or you know any collection of
units in a circuit. So the stack plot
you've seen this already right we're
just plotting the the voltages of all
the the inputs that you give to it. So
you can provide a single co composite
block to add to a stack block and it's
going to look for the all the neurons in
that composite block and plot their
activity or you can provide just a
vector of neurons in it and it's going
to plot the activity of each its vector
each one of those neurons. uh or you can
do like a main field plot where this is
just a population average of all the
membrane potentials and uh finally power
spectrum which is yeah uh is the power
the the average power spectrum across
all of the units in the composite
block. So and the the second example
that we will look at is this uh is this
network of pyramidal and inter neurons
that generate gamma rhythms and uh this
model was designed to capture attention
uh with the assumption that attention is
fundamentally rhythmic. So the idea is
that uh we'll have some excit excitatory
neurons that are particularly sensitized
to some stimula right and uh during this
interaction between the parameter
neurons and the inter neurons some of
the some of the parameal neurons will
align the rhythm and actually start this
gamma rhythm um that will align with
some ex external stimulus coming in and
that this how you essentially pay
attention to that stimulus over other
stimuli right and in the original work
this gamma rhythm is actually generated
it is entrenched inside a beta rhythm.
So the beta rhythm u um essentially
drives the gamma and uh in the tutorial
you will first generate the gamma rhythm
but if you want to add the the beta
rhythm as well on top of it you you will
see how to do that. Basically you just
need to add an external source that is a
cenosidal
current in the beta frequency.
Um right so
essentially um as I was saying there is
it's the negative feedback right from
the in neurons to the to the to the
parameter neurons that is uh and the
spike timings for that that they are
essential for generating uh attention
and when I say attention I mean
generating the rhythms right and if the
peak of the rhythm aligns with the
stimulus that's how uh you would attend
to that stimulus that's the assumption
And uh here you can see um and another
example of this happening right when we
have the excit excitatory neurons
starting well perfectly synchronized and
through the tonic activity of
inhibitoring units that you know
reciprocally connect to them. you will
see that it's only a subset of the excit
excitatory neurons winning right and uh
the the this subset on the bottom here
is what uh will remain synchronized okay
a few on top as well but this this
cluster uh will essentially win and stay
synchronized and you know whatever this
cluster is sensitive to uh the organism
will pay attention
to and of course this cluster can vary
according to uh timings for the spikes
Right. This was a perfectly aligned uh
spike to begin
with. So for the second tutorial, we
will build uh this this ping model uh
based on a paper from the literature and
this is a schematic uh for this. You can
see uh two subsets of excited excitatory
neurons and one population of inhibitory
neurons with these connections and the
input here is the the external input
that to begin with is constant but as I
was saying you can change this to some
cenosidal current to add the the beta
rhythm as well and uh yeah the
talisponders will focus on how this
rhythmic inhibition is more effective
than any type of you know asynchronous
inhibition and this was my last slide.
This is as an extra disclaimer. Uh
please uh for the session first navigate
to the introduction page. This is not a
notebook. This is only on the website
because it's mainly text. So go to
circuit models and then introduction and
uh because there are some important
points here partic particularly around
namespace in your blocks uh that is you
know important to know before you start
working with circuits and uh you know
the long story short is that namespace
is something uh that we were asking you
to add to your custom blocks but we're
keeping equal to nothing for now because
if we just use neurons uh there's no
hierarchal structure beneath the beneath
that neuron. So you don't need to carry
around this name space that qualifies
the name of every variable and of every
parameter. But when you have
hierarchical blocks like these cortical
blocks will be in both of both of the
examples then you need to supply the
name space. So in fact the the
connections are actually generated
appropriately.
Um so we so we keep track of where each
variable is coming from from which
neuron and how many terms should be
added to that connect input variable and
to then be able to substitute that input
variable into our differential
equations. So it's essential to have
this name space. So please uh read this
uh namespace section before you start
and then uh you can move on to the core
custodial model. Okay. Granted that uh
these examples including the challenge
problems they can get a bit lengthy. So
don't worry if you don't if you haven't
finished with both of them. You can do
the second one in your own time or maybe
on Friday uh if you want to. So yeah, if
there are no questions then feel free to